Dr. Edmondo Di Giuseppe

CONTACT National Research Council, Institute for Biometeorology CNR-IBIMET

INFORMATION Via dei Taurini, 19 Room 115

Rome, 00185 Italy *Work:* +39-0649937689

E-mail: e.digiuseppe@ibimet.cnr.it *ORCID identifier*: 0000-0002-6443-9106 Personal web page: edidigiu.github.io

RESEARCH INTERESTS My work bridges statistical methodology and software tools to analyze climate phenomena and their impacts. In particular, I use statistical tools such as functional clustering, Bayesian inference, and Extreme Value Distributions to analyze drought and heat waves by means of a combination of R and CDO operators to perform such analyses. I am also interested in the study of the effects of climate variability on cereals production and prices.

CURRENT POSITION

Researcher Nov 2018 to present

National Research Council, Institute for Biometeorology CNR-IBIMET

MED-GOLD

• Turning climate-related information into added value for traditional MEDiterranean Grape, OLive and Durum wheat food systems - PI: Dr Massimiliano Pasqui

PREVIOUS POSITIONS

Postdoctoral Research Assistant

Jan 2015 to Aug 2018

National Research Council, Institute for Biometeorology CNR-IBIMET

VOPA

- Volatility of agricultural commodity prices PI: Dr. Franco Miglietta.
- Study of the effects of *El Niño* on wheat worldwide production; Modeling of seasonal forecasts; Analysis of heat waves and their connection to large scale drivers.

Research Assistant Nov 2003 to Dec 2014

Agricultural Research Council, Research unit for Climatology and Meteorology applied to Agriculture CREA-CMA

AGROSCENARI

- Adaptation scenarios of Italian agriculture to climate change PI: Dr. Stanislao Esposito.
- Functional clustering of temperature and precipitation; Hierarchical Bayesian approach for predicting rainfall fields from lightning records.

CLIMANIMAL

- Heat warning model for dairy cattle PI: Dr. Stanislao Esposito.
- Statistical analysis of heat waves (temperature and air humidity); Logistic regression models for determining the relation between heat waves and dairy cattle mortality.

TEMPIO

- Seasonal forecast model for temperature and rainfall anomaly determination PI: Dr. Stanislao Esposito.
- Canonical Correlation Analysis for evaluating the relation between heat wave/dry spells and weather types.

CLIMAGRI

- Climate Change and Agriculture PI: Dr. Domenico Vento.
- Statistical analysis of rainfall, hydrometric levels, flow and dry/wet spells; Time series analysis; Models for return probability of rainfall extreme events (Generalized Extreme Value and Generalized Pareto distributions).

Research Assistant Mar to Oct 2003

Polytechnic University of Marche, Faculty of Economics Giorgio Fua´

COFIN 2001

• Complex dynamics and financial fragility in an agent-based model - PI: Professor Mauro Gallegati

EDUCATION

Ph.D., Methodological Statistics

December, 13 2013

Sapienza University of Rome, Roma, Italy

- Thesis: Statistical methods for the analysis of climatic phenomena
- Advisor: Professor Giovanna Jona Lasinio
- Area of Study: Statistical climatology

M.S., Economic Statistics

April, 8 2002

Sapienza University of Rome, Roma, Italy

- Thesis Topic: Evaluation of agent actions at local scale
- Adviser: Professor Sergio Bruno
- Area of Study: Microeconomy

REFEREED JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

- [1] Tarchiani V., Pasqui M., Parrish P., Rapisardi E., **Di Giuseppe E.** and Baldi M., 2019: Learning and teaching about seasonal climate forecasts: a Mediterranean educational experience toward operational climate services. *Advances in Science and Research*, 15, 257–262. doi:10.5194/asr-15-257-2019
- [2] Pasqui M. and **Di Giuseppe E.**, 2019: Climate change, future warming, and adaptation in Europe. *Animal Frontiers*, 9(1), 6–11. doi:10.1093/af/vfy036
- [3] Magno R., De Filippis T., Di Giuseppe E., Pasqui M., Rocchi L., and Gozzini B., 2018: Semi-Automatic Operational Service for Drought Monitoring and Forecasting in the Tuscany Region. *Geosciences*, 8(2), 49. doi:10.3390/geosciences8020049
- [4] Di Giuseppe E., Jona Lasinio G., Esposito S., Pasqui M., 2013: Functional clustering for Italian climate zones identification. *Theoretical and Applied Climatology*, 114(1-2): 39–54. doi:10.1007/s00704-012-0801-0
- [5] Mucciardi M., Bertuccelli P., **Di Giuseppe E.** 2012: Local Spatial Modeling of Meteorological Variables. *Advances in Mathematical and Computational Methods*, 2(3): 1–14, ISSN 2160-0635, 10.5729/amcm.vol2.issue3.1

BOOK CHAPTERS

[6] Di Giuseppe E., Jona Lasinio G., Pasqui M. and Esposito S., 2014: Predicting Rainfall Fields from Lightning Records: A Hierarchical Bayesian Approach. In: Lanzarone E., Ieva F.: *The Contribution of Young Researchers to Bayesian Statistics*, Springer Proceedings in Mathematics & Statistics, Springer International Publishing, Vol. 63, pp. 95–99. doi:http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-02084-6_19

CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS

- [1] E. Rapisardi, M. Pasqui, V. Tarchiani, E. Di Giuseppe, and M. Baldi, 2018: Training on Seasonal Climate Forecast: enabling a more informed climate related risk management and services, *EGU General Assembly 2018*, EGU2018-12398
- [2] R. Magno, M. Pasqui and **E. Di Giuseppe**, 2016: Analysis of changes in drought occurrence over the Mediterranean Basin using multiple time scales SPI index, *EMS Annual Meeting Abstracts*, Vol. 13, EMS2016-425, 16th EMS/11th ECAC.
- [3] M. Pasqui and **E. Di Giuseppe**, 2016: Large scale atmospheric drivers for heat waves in the Mediterranean Basin, *Geophysical Research Abstracts*, Vol. 18, EGU2016-14124-1, EGU General Assembly 2016.
- [4] Magno R., Angeli L., Chiesi M., De Filippis T., **Di Giuseppe E.**, Pasqui M., Rocchi L., Zabini F., 2015: Implementation of a national drought monitoring and forecasting system, Conference: *Earth Observation for Water Cycle Science 2015*, ESA-ESRIN Frascati, Rome.

- [5] B. Parisse, **E. Di Giuseppe**, M. Scaglione, S. Esposito, 2014: Spatio-temporal distribution of calibrated Hargreaves-Samani coefficients in Italy, *Proceedings of XVII AIAM Conference: Role of agro-meteorology in the new agricultural policies*, Roma, 10–12 Giugno.
- [6] Pasqui M., Melani S., Pasi F., Gozzini B., Gaetani M., **Di Giuseppe E.**, Levizzani V., 2013: Retrospective analysis of synoptic favourable conditions for deep convective events in the Mediterranean Sea, *European Conference on Severe Storms*, Helsinki; 06/2013
- [7] M. Baldi, S. Esposito, M. Pasqui, E. Di Giuseppe, F. Guarnieri, 2010: An operational seasonal forecast service for agriculture in italy: the Tempio project, *Abstracts of the Technical Conference on Changing Climate and Demands for Climate Services for Sustainable Development*, WMO/TD-No. 1521, Antalya, Turkey, 16–18 February.
- [8] S. Giavante, E. Di Giuseppe, S. Esposito, 2009: Flat steps models for the analysis of temperature and precipitation italian time series from 1961 to 2007, *Statistical Methods for the analysis of large data-sets Book of short papers*, 427–430.
- [9] M. Pasqui, E. Di Giuseppe, S. Quaresima, F. Guarnieri, S. Giavante, S. Esposito, 2008: An atmospheric regime characterization of monthly seasonal forecast in Italy based on weather type classification, *Advances in Weather and Circulation Type* Classifications & Applications (COST 733 Mid-term Conference), 22–25 October 2008, Krakow, Poland, pag. 69.
- [10] Baldi M., Esposito S., Di Giuseppe E., Pasqui M., Maracchi G., Vento D., 2008: Seasonal forecasting climatic anomalies for agriculture in Italy: the TEMPIO Project, EMS Annual Meeting Abstracts–European Conference on Applied Climatology (ECAC), Amsterdam, Netherlands 29 September–3 October, EMS2008-A-00519 European Meteorological Society.
- [11] F. Guarnieri, **E. Di Giuseppe**, B. Gozzini, F. Meneguzzo, R. Magno, G. Maracchi, M Pasqui, 2007: Analysis of historical series of hourly pluviometric data in Central Italy, *7th EMS Annual Meeting/8th ECAM Abstracts*, Vol. 4, EMS2007-A-00320.
- [12] **Di Giuseppe E.**, Esposito S., Vento D., 2007: A comparison of models in return levels calculating, *IUGG–XXIV International Union of Geodesy and Geophysic*, Perugia, Italy 2-13 July, IAHS/HW2003 4570, pag. 626, ISBN: 978-88-95852-25-4.
- [13] F. Guarnieri, E. Di Giuseppe, B. Gozzini, F. Meneguzzo, R. Magno, G. Maracchi, M. Pasqui, 2007: Analysis of historical series of hourly pluviometric data in Central Italy, 7th EMS Annual Meeting / 8th ECAM Abstracts, Vol. 4, EMS2007-A-00320.
- [14] Mangianti De Angelis F., Epifani C., Epifani R., **Di Giuseppe E.**, 2005: A climatic analysis of some Italian tourist sites. A future scenario for tourism, *WMO Technical Conference on Climate as a Resource*, Beijing, China, 1–2 November.
- [15] Ferrari R., Pasqui M., Bottai L., Esposito S., **Di Giuseppe E.**, 2005: Assessment of soil erosion estimate based on a high temporal resolution rainfall dataset, *EMS 5th Annual Meeting Abstracts*, EMS05-A-00285 European Meteorological Society.
- [16] C. Epifani, **E. Di Giuseppe**, S. Esposito, D. Vento, 2005: Extreme events of precipitation over Italy and their probability of occurrence, *EMS 5th Annual Meeting Abstracts*, EMS05-A-00311 European Meteorological Society.
- [17] **E. Di Giuseppe**, D. Vento, C. Epifani, S. Esposito, 2005: Analysis of dry and wet spells from 1870 to 2000 in four Italian sites, *EGU European Geosciences Union, Geophysical Research Abstracts*, Vol. VII, 07712
- [18] Vento D., Esposito S., Epifani C., Di Giuseppe E., 2004: Analysis of Italian precipitation regimes with reference to extreme events, EMS 4th Annual Meeting Abstracts—ECAC-5th Conference on Applied Climatology, Vol. 1, 00249, EMS European Meteorological Society.

[19] **Di Giuseppe E.**, Vento D., Esposito S., Epifani C., 2004: Analysis of heavy rainfall in very high temporal resolution in Italy during last 10 years, *ICCP-14th International Conference on Clouds and Precipitation Proceedings*, Vol. I, pagg. 285–288.

CONFERENCE TALKS

- [20] **E. Di Giuseppe**, G. Giulioni and M. Pasqui, 2017: Climate Effects on Wheat Markets: an Agent-based Approach, 1st Hamburg Workshop on Agent-based Modeling of Environmental Challenges and Climate Policy.
- [21] **Di Giuseppe E.**, Jona Lasinio G., Pasqui M. and Esposito S., 2013: Predicting Rainfall Fields from Lightning Records: A Hierarchical Bayesian Approach, *First Bayesian Young Statisticians Meeting-BAYSM 2013*, Milan, Italy, June 5-6, 2013.
- [22] Di Giuseppe E., Jona Lasinio G., Pasqui M., Esposito S., 2012: Point Processes for modeling lightning data, *IX Conference on Geostatistics for Envioronmental Appli*cations geoENV2012, Valencia, Spain, September 19–21, 2012, Editor: J. Jaime Gómez-Hernández, ISBN: 978-84-8363-924-5.
- [23] **Di Giuseppe E.**, Jona Lasinio G., Pasqui M., Esposito S., 2010: Functional clustering of Temperature and Precipitation data for Italian climate zones determination, *Gfkl-Cladag Joint Meeting 2010*, Book of Abstract 8-10 September 2010, Firenze, Italy, pp. 151–152.
- [24] **Di Giuseppe E.**, Jona Lasinio G., Esposito S. and Pasqui M., 2010: A functional data approach for climate zones identification, *11th International Meeting on Statistical Climatology Program&Abstracts*, pp. 140–141, 12–16 July 2010, Edinburgh, Scotland.

CONFERENCE POSTERS

[25] V. Tarchiani, E. Rapisardi, M. Pasqui, P. Parrish, E. Di Giuseppe, and M. Baldi, 2017: Learning and teaching about seasonal climate forecasts: a Mediterranean educational experience toward operational climate services. In: EMS Annual Meeting: European Conference for Applied Meteorology and Climatology 2017, EMS2017-93.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

WMO Regional Training Center (RTC) - Italy

- Instructor for Training Course 2015, 2016, 2017, and 2018.
 - Responsible for R practical training.
 - Authored material at http://edidigiu.github.io/code.html.

Professional Service

Referee Service

• DCAI 2015: 12th International Symposium on Distributed Computing and Artificial Intelligence

SOFTWARE SKILLS Computer Programming:

• UNIX shell scripting

Numerical Analysis:

• R, CDO Operators

Version Control:

• Git, Svn

Desktop Editing and Productivity Software:

- Vim
- TEX (LATEX, BIBTEX), Markdown
- Microsoft Office, OpenOffice, LibreOffice, Google Docs
- ArcGis, GRASS

Operating Systems:

• Apple OS X, Linux, Microsoft Windows

REFERENCES AVAILABLE TO CONTACT

Dr. Massimiliano Pasqui (e-mail: m.pasqui@ibimet.cnr.it; phone: +39-0649937615)

- Permanent Researcher, National Research Council, Institute for Biometeorology,
- National Research Council, Institute for Biometeorology, Via dei Taurini, 19 Rome, 00185 Italy
- * Dr. Pasqui was my postdoctoral supervisor.

Prof. Giovanna Jona Lasinio (e-mail: giovanna.jonalasinio@uniroma1.it; phone: +39 06 49910473)

- Associate Professor, Sapienza University of Rome
- Sapienza University of Rome
 P.le Aldo Moro n. 5 Edificio ex Fac. Scienze Statistiche Rome, 00185 Italy
- * Prof. Jona Lasinio was my PhD Thesis Advisor.

Dr. Stanislao Esposito (e-mail: stanislao.esposito@crea.gov.it; phone: 06 7005413-102)

- Permanent Resercher, Research Council for Agriculture-CREA
- ♦ via della Navicella,2 00184 Rome, Italy
- * Dr. Esposito was my tutor during the experience in AGROSCENARI, TEMPIO, CLI-MANIMAL and CLIMAGRI projects.

Prof. Gianfranco Giulioni (e-mail: gianfranco.giulioni@unich.it; phone: +39 0854537584)

- Associate Professor, G. d'Annunzio University of Chieti-Pescara
- ⋄ G. d'Annunzio University of Chieti-Pescara Viale Pindaro 42 - 65127 - Pescara - Italy
- * Prof. Giulioni was my tutor during the experience in COFIN project.

More Information Publications in Italian language and auxiliary documents can be found at ResearchGate, Mendeley and Google Scholar.

DATE December 27, 2018